A Lo & Hu Co-Production
罗胡联制有限公司  出品
RAINING IN THE MOUNTAIN
片名: 空 山 灵 雨
Presented by King HU, WU Sau-yee
出品人: 胡金铨  胡树儒
Executive Producers LO Kai-Muk, CHUNG Ling
监制: 罗开睦  钟玲
Starring HSU Feng as White Fox,
主演: 徐枫 饰 白狐
SUN Yueh as Esquire Wen, TUNG Lin as Chiu Ming,
孙越 饰 文安   佟林 饰 邱明
WU Chia-hsiang as Master Wu Wai,
吴家骧 饰 悟外法师
WU Ming-tsai as Gold Lock, LU Chun as Hui Wen
吴明才 饰 金锁   鲁纯 饰 慧文
Guest Starring SHIH Chun as Hui Tung
客串: 石隽 饰 慧通
Art Director King HU
美术: 胡金铨
Martial Arts Director WU Ming-tsai
武术指导: 吴明才
Edited by King HU
剪辑: 胡金铨  萧南
Cinematography Henry CHAN
摄影: 陈俊杰
Music by NG Tai Kong
音乐: 吴大江
Assistant Directors TUNG Lin, Fred TAN Han-Chung
副导: 佟林  但汉章
Produced by HON Kap-Chan
制片: 韩甲振  陈嘉雯
Written and Directed by King HU
编导: 胡金铨
Three Treasures Temple is just beyond that shrine.
过了那座小庙  才是三宝寺的地界
See that senior monk?
你看到那位大和尚了吗
He's the temple guardian.
他就是护庙的韦陀
As long as he's on duty,
有他守在这儿
outsiders dare not set foot here.
闲杂人等休想越雷池半步
Brother.
师傅
Please follow me.
请这边走  我带路
Who is he?
谁
Brother Hui Ssu.
慧思师傅
Welcome!
三位施主
This is my concubine.
这是小妾
Madame.
如夫人
Esquire Wen,
文居士
the Abbot sent me to welcome you.
师父特地派贫僧来恭迎三位施主
Thank you!
不敢当
When I received the Abbot's letter
我一接到老禅师的信
I rushed right over.
马上就赶来了
How is the old master?
他老人家的身子怎么样了
Not well.
不太好
He had a fainting spell two days ago,
前天痰上来了  一度昏迷不醒
but he's a little better today.
今天好了点儿
I'm afraid his time is not long.
大概离西游之际不远了
This is the famous Three Treasures Temple.
这就是天下闻名的三宝寺
What are the "three treasures"?
这庙里有哪三件宝物啊
Not worldly but spiritual treasures:
这三宝不是世俗所说的宝物
the Buddha, the Dharma and the monastic community.
是佛家所谓的佛  法  僧
I don't understand.
我不懂那些个
Do you mean Tripitaka's...?
你说的那个什么玄
The Mahayana Sutra in Tripitaka's own hand.
玄奘法师手抄的《大乘起信论》残卷
How much is it worth?
那值多少钱呐
It's priceless.
无价之宝
I've brought aged ginseng from the north.
我带来了一些关东老山参
Perhaps it can help the Abbot.
也许有点儿用处
Many thanks!
尽人事吧
The Abbot told me to inform you
师父叫贫僧带口信给居士
that before he dies,
他老人家想在西游之前
he must name a successor.
选出一位新住持
Because we've so many worthy monks,
因为三宝寺庙大人多
he's asked lay friends to assist him.
就请了几位方外的朋友  来商量商量
Who else has he invited?
除了我之外  还请了些什么人
I don't know.
这就不清楚了
The Abbot also thanks you
师父叫贫僧特地向居士致意
for all the donations
这几年
you've given us over the years
居士布施三宝寺不下十万两银子
and your warm support.
又处处照应庙里的和尚
Don't mention it.
这点儿小意思  不要提了
The Abbot has another request.
师父还有个请求
- Does the temple need more...? - No, we're financially sound.
- 是不是还要  - 不不不  庙里能维特
He asks you
师父请求居士
to lend your support to the new abbot.
对将来选出的新住持多多照应
But of course.
一定一定
Brother Hui Ssu.
慧思师傅
Who do you expect him to choose?
依你看  老禅师想传衣钵给谁呢
It's not for me to speculate.
传法大事  贫僧不敢妄加揣测
- Let them take your luggage. - Yes, sir!
- 管家  把东西交给他们  - 是
- Take the valet to his room.
- 带管家到厢房  - 是
This way.
请
Your meal will be served shortly.
两位歇一会儿  斋饭马上就送来
Thank you. You're dismissed.
好  你去忙吧  不要招呼了
Let's eat.
吃饭呐
Go ahead. I'll just be a minute.
你先吃  我就来
Hurry!
走
Up there!
上去
There it is!
是这儿
Come on!
走
( No Admittance )
( 僧俗止步 )
It must be here somewhere. Keep watch!
大概是这儿  你给我看着点儿
OK.
好
No!
没有啊
What does it look like?
那本经是什么样的
It's a long scroll.
听说是个长手卷
Wait...
你等一等
The door's unlocked.
那门好像没锁上啊
Unlocked?
门没锁上  不会吧
Look!
- 你看  - 没锁啊
Brother Hui Wen!
二师哥
What is it?
什么事
The Scripture Hall door is unlocked.
那个藏经楼的门没锁
Yes, I opened it.
噢  是我开的
Then left it unlocked?
- 那就不用锁了  - 唉
What'd he say?
怎么样
He said to leave it open.
二师哥说不用锁了
This way.
走这边
Was it a trying journey?
您这一路上辛苦了
Not so bad.
哪里
Good day.
二位施主
Take the luggage to the guest rooms.
扛到客房去
Madame!
施主
Over there!
那边
What is it?
怎么
Strange!
奇怪
Brother Hui Tung, who is that?
慧通师傅  这是谁
Esquire Wen's new concubine.
文安新娶的如夫人
Esquire Wen?
文安
The wealthy landowner from Chiang Tung?
就是那个江东的那个大财主
I know him.
我认识他
Unbelievable!
想不到
You know the woman?
你认识这个女人
Yes.
认识
Who is she?
谁
She's called White Fox. A thief.
女飞贼白狐
A thief? Are you sure?
女飞贼  不会吧
It's her.
是她
Did you see it, General?
将军  您瞧见没有
She has a master key.
她身上还带着百合锁
Oh? I didn't notice.
这我倒没留神
I arrested her once in the north,
我在关外当差的时候抓过她
but she escaped.
押在半路  她跑了
I don't know Esquire Wen very well,
我和文安虽然是泛泛之交
but I should inform him
可是他娶了一个女飞贼
that he has married a thief.
我应该告诉他一声
Brother Hui Tung, please arrange a meeting.
慧通师傅  你去约一约文安
Very well!
好
General, wait!
等一等  将军
What is it?
怎么
There's more to this than meets the eye.
这里边大概另有文章
You were too careless.
你也太沉不住气了
You brought me here
我来这鬼地方
to steal that damn scroll for you.
就是为了给你偷那本破书
So what was I supposed to do?
要不然我来干什么
Wait for the right time!
那你得慢慢来呀
This temple food is awful!
这么大个庙  吃这种玩意儿
Everyone here eats the same food.
连庙里的人都吃这个
Those leading spiritual lives for ego luxuries.
修行的人不能讲究享乐
I'm not leading a spiritual life!
我又不修行
Given your history,
你从小就不干好事
perhaps you should!
实在应该修行修行
Nonsense!
你少扯闲片儿
I don't understand...
我就不明白
With your wealth you can buy anything.
你家财万贯  要什么有什么
What do you want with a ragged old scroll?
还要那本破书干什么
What do you know?
你懂什么
It's the Mahayana Sutra,
这是当年大唐玄奘法师
hand-copied by the great monk Tripitaka.
亲手抄的《大乘起信论》
It's priceless.
是无价之宝
Money can't buy it.
多少钱也买不到
What good is it?
又不能当饭吃
It's one of a kind.
这本卷子  普天下就这么一份
I've long dreamed of possessing it.
我想了好几年了
I'll get it for you as soon as I can
好  我尽快把经给你弄到手
and then get the hell out of here.
早点儿离开这个鬼地方
I'm telling you,
我老实告诉你
I don't want to hang around this dump!
我不愿意在这儿耗着
Don't be rash. I've got a plan.
你可别胡来  我有一定的步骤
Forget it! I'm getting out of here!
我可没有这个耐心玩
I'll give you your money back.
这样吧  我把钱退给你
Hire someone else. I quit.
我先走  你另请高明
Why are you so angry?
你何必这么大火呢
I don't like waiting around!
本来嘛  我就不喜欢拖拖拉拉的
OK, OK!
好了  好了  快吃饭吧
Hey! Keep your hands off!
你干什么你
You paid me to steal the scroll
我告诉你  你有钱  我给你偷书
and that's all you'll get!
少来别的
So now you're a lady of virtue, eh?
你可真是三贞九烈啊
Shut up!
你少废话
We had an understanding, didn't we?
咱可是有言在先
I sell my skills, not my body!
我是卖艺不卖身
I'm not a whore!
可不能老尺加一啊
Keep it down, will you?
你小声点儿行不行
- Why should I? - Please, my lady.
- 怕什么  - 姑奶奶
Who is it?
谁呀
It's me.
是贫僧
Brother Hui Wen.
慧文师傅
Greetings.
施主
Come, I'll introduce you.
我给你引荐引荐
This is Brother Hui Wen.
这位是慧文师傅
We've already met... at the Scripture Hall.
刚才在藏经楼  已见过如夫人了
Fortunately, he's our friend.
还好  慧文师傅是自己人
He's the Abbot's number two disciple
现在是智严老住持的二弟子
and will very likely be the next abbot.
将来是三宝寺的新住持
We can't be certain of that!
可千万不要这么说
Don't worry.
你放心好了
My words carry weight with the Abbot.
我的话在老住持面前  多少有点份量
I'll leave you two to your business.
你们二位谈公事  我失陪了
Fine.
好
Your support is invaluable.
施主的话自然是一言九鼎了
Did you get my letter?
贫僧的信  您收到了吗
Yes.
收到了
I can almost guarantee you the position.
十成的把握不敢说  七八成总有
Did you receive my letter?
我的信  你也收到了吧
Yes.
收到了
If I become the new abbot,
万一贫僧要是接了衣钵
the scroll is yours!
那本卷子一定奉上
Then it's a deal!
好  咱们一言为定
We businessmen place trust above all.
我们做生意的人  讲究的就是信用
I'll speak to the Abbot in a bit.
等一会儿我到老住持那儿
I'll sound him out for you.
给你探探口气
Please, don't be hasty.
也不能操之过急
General Wang is pressing Hui Tung's case!
王将军大力推荐师哥啊
Wang's a soldier, not a scholar.
王骥是武人
The Abbot won't necessarily heed his counsel.
老住持不一定听他的
Let's hope not.
但愿如此
I must be going.
我告辞了
OK.
好
One more thing:
还有
your concubine may move freely about,
如夫人到处逛逛  倒是无所谓
but she mustn't arouse suspicion.
就是要不着痕迹
Someone's outside.
有人
Gold Lock!
金锁
Over here!
过来
Let him go.
不要追了
Yes.
是
Who is he?
这是谁呀
He's the famous Master Wu Wai.
这就是天下闻名的悟外法师
What is he known for?
他是干什么的
He's a devoted lay Buddhist.
他是维摩诘一类的人
I don't get it.
我不懂
Although he's a layman, he knows
他虽没出家  可是精通佛法
the sutras better than most monks do!
道行比一般和尚都高啊
Then what's he doing with all those women?
他信佛  怎么还带一大堆女人
He's immune to sensual pleasures.
到他这境界  已经心中无色了
Him? He looks like an old lecher.
我才不相信呢  我看他是个老色迷呀
Nonsense! Even the emperor defers to him.
别胡说  当今皇上都要让他三分
Halt!
放
It's so good you've come!
你来了  好极了
Your Reverence!
老禅师
Arise, arise!
起来  快起来
Get up!
起身
Esquire Wen.
文公子
General Wang, it's been a while.
王将军  久违了
Over a year since we last met.
总有一年多没见了
Master Wu Wai travels in style, doesn't he?
这位悟外法师的气派  可真不小
I believe he too has come here
我看悟外法师
for the succession.
大概也是为传衣钵而来
Perhaps.
也许
Who do you think will be chosen?
你看这衣钵应该传给谁
Who do you think?
将军看呢
Brother Hui Tung, without a doubt.
我看是非慧通师傅莫属
Brother Hui Tung is very clever.
慧通师傅确实很有谋略
Over here.
你过来
Give it to me.
交给我
This food is for Master Wu Wai.
这是悟外居士的荤菜
I know. Now give it to me!
我知道  你交给我吧
Go on!
你去吧
Who will Your Reverence pick?
老禅师心目中是什么人
My mind is unsteady these days
这些日子心神不定
and my old body is failing me.
大概这个臭皮囊不顶事了
That is why I seek your advice.
所以才急着找你来商量商量
The temple is a huge responsibility.
主持这么大的庙不容易
If I choose unwisely,
如果选错了人
disputes will arise.
将来必起争端
General Wang and Esquire Wen have also come.
这趟我还请了王骥和文安来了
If there is a disagreement,
万一将来起争端
they can arbitrate.
他们也好出头说几句话
What are your criteria for choosing the new abbot?
那么在人选方面  是否有个范围
I have none.
没有
It doesn't matter...
我想了好几天了
...whether he is a monk or a layman,
不论是僧是俗
so long as he is enlightened.
只要有慧根就能传法度人
Hui Ssu,
慧思
go and fetch Master Wu Wai's meal.
你去把法师的荤菜拿来
Will do.
是
Brother Hui Tung.
师哥
I'm delivering Master Wu Wai's meal.
我正要给法师拿荤菜
I'll take it. You prepare a pot of tea.
我送进去  你去沏茶
OK.
是
Your Reverence, when are you planning to choose a successor?
那么老禅师准备什么时候传衣钵呢
In a few days.
就这几天
But there's a worldly matter to attend to first.
不过我还有点儿俗事未了
A convict has purchased a permit to become a monk here.
有个流犯买了度牒  在这里出家
Let's take a rest.
歇会吧
Nobody's around. I'll take it off.
这儿没人  卸了吧
Thank you, officer!
谢谢你  老大爷
Not at all.
谢什么
We've been through a lot together.
咱们相聚一场  就是有缘呢
Is this Chiu Ming?
- 这是邱明吧  - 是
Yes.
这是三宝寺的文书
May I see the Abbot?
智严师傅在不在
The Abbot sent me to take charge of him.
师父交代过  你把人交给我就行了
Make good use of your time here, friend.
好吧兄弟  你就在庙里好好修行
Perhaps we'll meet again.
咱们再见了
Officer!
老大爷
I don't know how to thank you!
我也没什么话好说了
Please don't. Get up!
起来  不要这样
Kneel.
跪下
This is the Abbot and this is Master Wu Wai.
这位是师父  那位是悟外法师
I bow to you, Reverence.
弟子邱明  参见师父
Who is your master?
谁是你师父
You are my master.
你就是我师父
Do you sincerely wish to become a monk?
你是来出家的  还是来避祸的
I do.
出家
You are a convicted criminal.
你是充军发配的流犯
What are you charged with?
犯的什么罪
Theft.
盗窃
So you did transgress.
你犯了偷戒
No. I was falsely accused.
弟子没犯戒  被人陷害
By whom?
谁陷害
Lieutenant Chang Cheng.
指挥张诚
How did that happen?
张诚怎么陷害你
My brother was a woodblock printer.
家兄是书馆刻工
Our family owned a rare edition of the Diamond Sutra.
家里藏着一部咸通版的《金刚经》
Chang Cheng wanted to buy it.
张诚想买
My brother wouldn't sell it.
家兄不肯
So Chang Cheng accused us of theft.
张诚就罗织以偷窃罪
Arise.
你起来
And then?
后来呢
He beat my brother to death in court
当堂用非刑打死家兄
and I was sentenced to serve in the army.
弟子叛了个充军
Have you ever met Chang Cheng?
你见过张诚吗
No.
没有
If you happened to meet him, what would you do?
如果你见了他  你怎么办
Nothing.
不怎么办
You bear no grudge?
你不怨
Start by mopping the temple floor.
你先把这庙里的地洗干净吧
Go and get the goods.
去叫人来抬货啊
Hurry! Give it over!
快点儿  递过来啊
Calm down.
别急  别急
Be careful!
小心点儿
- Not enough! - It's plenty.
- 这多少钱呐  - 不少了
I'm taking a loss...
两吊半呐  这不够本儿啊
Seven strings of 100...
七吊  一百
Six strings of 320...
六吊  三百二
Six strings of 910...
六吊  九百一
Seven strings of 460...
七吊  四百六
Four strings of 650.
四吊  六百五
Stop!
停
Wrong again!
你怎么又错了
You! Do it over!
就你一个人  再算一遍
Esquire Wen.
文兄
General Wang.
王将军
I just saw something strange.
文兄  我刚才看见一件怪事
While Wu Wai was preaching, his attendants
悟外法师讲经的时候
were bathing in full view of the monks!
居然让侍女当着和尚的面洗澡
Where?
在哪里
Just over the hill.
就在后山
This way of propagating Buddhism
这种弘扬佛法的办法
is really something new.
倒是别开生面
Going a bit far, wouldn't you say?
这有点儿太过份了吧
Very profound.
玄妙之至
I think I'll have a look.
我倒真想去开开眼界
They're still there. Follow me.
他们还没散  我带你去啊
OK.
好
Please.
请
What sect is it?
这算哪宗啊
No idea...
不大清楚
Gentlemen, the Abbot...
两位施主
will see you now.
师父有请
Very well.
好  好
This way.
这边儿请
- Please.
- 请  - 请
Please follow me.
请跟我来
Please.
请
- Gentlemen. - Your Reverence.
- 二位施主  - 老禅师
The Abbot had matters to attend to
师父说  昨天俗务缠身
and couldn't see you earlier. Apologies.
没机会向二位请教  很抱歉
He hopes you're comfortable here.
师父还问  你们二位还住得舒服吧
Very much so!
很好  很好
The Abbot says, when his successor takes over,
师父说  将来新住持揭了示
if there's a dispute,
万一起了什么争执
he'd like you two to mediate.
请二位说句公道话
Rest assured, Reverence.
老禅师  您放心
We'll do as you wish.
一定遵命
Very well.
那就好
Your Reverence,
老禅师
which of the monks
不知道老禅师
will you choose as your successor?
预备传衣钵给哪位师傅啊
Each of them is worthy,
他们个个是佛
each is perfect in his own way.
就像水银泄地  粒粒成圆
You two have done much for me over the years.
二位施主这些年来  帮了我不少忙
How can I repay you?
我有什么地方能为二位效劳呢
I've heard Tripitaka's handwritten Mahayana Sutra is kept here.
久闻贵宝刹里藏着一部玄奘法师手抄的《大乘起信论》
Would it be possible to see it?
不知道能不能瞻仰瞻仰
By all means.
这个好办
Is Esquire Wen also interested?
文施主也有兴致吗
I've long yearned to see the treasured scroll.
早就想见识见识这个旷世之宝
Ha! It's no treasure,
什么宝物
just a roll of tattered paper.
不过是一堆烂纸
It truly is a priceless treasure.
真不愧是无价之宝
Incomparable!
叹为观止
Its true value lies in its meaning.
这卷子的用处是它的文意
But of course!
当然  当然
Brother Hui Ssu, lead the way.
慧思师傅  带路吧
Let's go!
走
- Hey, what's that? - Indeed.
- 什么东西啊  - 是啊
- Let's go and check it out. - Sure.
- 上去看一看  - 好
Wait a second.
大家等一下
What is it?
什么事嘛
- Let's take a look. - At what?
- 快跟我上来看一看  - 看什么
The ground's covered with them...
怎么弄得一地都是啊
Careful!
大家小心一点儿啊
They look like prayer beads.
这大概是念珠吧
They're unstrung!
念珠散了
Hurry!
来来来  大家帮忙捡一下  快点儿
Give them to him.
把捡起来的念珠交给他
Here's one...
这儿还有
- Keep looking. - OK.
- 四处再找一找  - 好
Go and look by the back door.
你到后门口去看看
- Are there some more? - No.
- 还有没有  - 没有了
- There are some here. - Gather them.
- 这儿还有  - 拿过来啊
- They're gone. - Go look.
- 不见了  - 找找
Any more?
还有没有啦
Here's one more!
这儿还有了
You! Who are you?
你  你是什么人
Chiu Ming.
邱明
What did you do before you came here?
你以前是干什么的
I was sentenced to serve in the army
充军发配的流犯
but I bought a permit to become a monk instead.
现在买了度牒  出家当和尚
Since you're a monk now,
你既然依皈佛门
what are you doing with these women?
为什么还要跟女人鬼混
Watch what you say, sir.
施主  说话请慎重点
Outrageous!
混帐
You dare lecture me?
你敢教训我
This is preposterous!
真是岂有此理
Let's go! Don't be nosy.
快走吧  别管这件事了
Hurry! Go!
快走  走吧
What are you doing?
你干嘛
The hook!
爪
All for a raggedy scroll...
为了那张残卷
Sit.
坐下
Chiu Ming, tell no one about this,
邱明  这件事不要声张
or it will be trouble for you.
传出去  对你不利
Understood.
是
The man who struck you was Chang Cheng.
那个打你的人就是指挥张诚
Don't be afraid.
你也不用怕
Kneel.
跪下
Henceforth, you shall guard the Scripture Hall.
日后这藏经阁就归你管
The responsibility is too great for me.
这  弟子恐怕担不了这么大的责任
Why is that?
你倒说说看
I've heard Tripitaka's handwritten
弟子听说
Mahayana Sutra is kept there.
藏经楼放着玄奘法师手抄的经卷
If something should happen to it...
万一出了事
That is a worldly view.
这都是世俗之见
The old scroll has no real value.
那几张破纸没什么了不起
Brother.
师弟
Take this ginseng to Master Wu Wai.
你把这人参送给悟外法师
Tell him it's a gift from Esquire Wen.
就说是文安居士送的
Yes.
是
Brother Hui Ssu,
师弟  师弟
I'd like a word with you.
我有话跟你说
When did he take the vows?
他什么时候剃度的
This morning.
今天早上
Why were you two in the Scripture Hall?
你们上藏经楼干什么
The Abbot appointed him guardian of the Scripture Hall.
师父吩咐  以后藏经楼归他管
A convict guarding the scriptures...
叫那个流犯管藏经楼
What's the deeper meaning of this?
这又是什么禅机
Perhaps Master will choose Hui Ssu.
我看师父也许会传衣钵给三师弟
No, he won't!
不会  不会
Hui Ssu is too young.
慧思太年轻
You've managed the temple's assets for many years.
再说这么多年  庙产都是由你管
No one is better suited than you.
别人来  这法轮他推不转啊
Please don't say that!
可千万别这么说
If Hui Tung should overhear,
这话要是叫大师哥听见了
there'd be no end of trouble.
可不得了啊
You're both talking rubbish!
你们说的都是废话
Don't be foolhardy!
你可不能太冒失
My way is better.
还是我的办法好
Listen... wait...!
我跟你说
Sir!
施主
Sir, wait!
施主  请留步
Let us begin.
我们现在来了
Your Reverence!
老禅师
I am your devoted lay friend,
我不但是您老人家方外的好朋友
but I'm also governor of this district.
也是这里的地方官
There is a matter we must get to the bottom of.
这件事情我们非弄个水落石出不可
Feel free to speak.
施主有话请尽管说
Are you aware
这个人的出身
of this man's background?
您老人家知道不知道
Please go on.
那你说说看
He's a criminal.
这个人原是乡间无赖
A thief!
偷了东西
He was arrested and sentenced to the army.
被抓到官厅里  叛了个充军
I don't know how he got the money
不知道哪里弄来的钱
to buy his way out.
买度牒赎了罪
His Reverence is aware of this.
这些师父都知道
It was the Abbot himself who administered the vows.
是师父亲自给他剃度的
Your Reverence has led a spiritual life,
老禅师  您在这里多年静修
indifferent to worldly affairs.
不问世俗间的事情
Do you question my judgment?
你说我失查
No, no! All I'm saying is
不  我是说
you may be unaware of his background.
您老人家对他的身世也许不清楚
But let's not dwell on that.
先不管这些
If he'd reformed, I'd let it go.
他要是能痛改前非  也就罢了
But he's up to his old tricks!
可是  他贼性难改
Oh? How has he erred?
他有什么不规矩的举动
He was stealing in the Scripture Hall.
就是刚才  他到藏经楼去偷东西
Luckily, Chang Cheng was on hand to stop him.
幸亏张诚看见了  他才没能得手
It's a lie!
他瞎说
Your Reverence...
老禅师
I have reported the incident to the Abbot.
刚才的事  贫僧已经回禀过师父了
General Wang.
王将军
May I question Lieutenant Chang?
我可不可以问张指挥几句话
Of course.
请
Lieutenant Chang.
张指挥
How do you know he was stealing?
你怎么知道他是去偷东西的
As it happens,
是这样的
I saw him sneak into the Scripture Hall.
他鬼鬼祟祟地溜进藏经楼
I grew suspicious and followed him.
我就起了疑心跟进去
When I asked him what he was doing,
我问他到这儿来干什么
he couldn't give me a straight answer.
他支支吾吾的答不出来
Then I knew he was up to something.
我马上就猜到了  他图谋不轨
You guessed, Lieutenant?
张指挥是猜到的
Lt. Chang is an officer of the law.
张指挥是提刑出身
He's familiar with the likes of Chiu Ming.
对这类人最清楚了
Wasn't Lt. Chang himself an outlaw
听说张指挥在投效朝廷之前
before he joined the constabulary?
也在江湖上混过
Let's not digress.
先不要谈这些题外的话
Chiu Ming was stealing
邱明由藏经楼偷了东西出来
and Lt. Chang confronted him.
张诚问了他几句
In shame and anger,
不料他恼羞成怒
he threw Lt. Chang from the Scripture Hall!
还把张诚从楼上打了下来
Chiu Ming! Is it true?
邱明  有没有这回事
Yes.
有
General Wang,
王将军
I've heard that Lt. Chang is a martial artist.
听说张指挥的武功造诣很高啊
Indeed he is!
相当不错
Then how is it that he was thrown down the stairs?
那怎么会让他从楼上打下来呢
No, no, no! This is a sacred place!
不不不不  这里是佛门净地
I would never violate its sanctity by fighting.
我怎么能够跟他动武呢
Lt. Chang would've arrested him anywhere else.
要是在外边儿  张诚立刻就抓他归案
But the temple
可是  现在是在庙里
is under the Abbot's jurisdiction.
就请老禅师处理吧
Hui Tung, what do you think should be done?
慧通
According to the rules,
依照庙规
he should be expelled for thievery.
他犯了偷戒  应该逐出门墙
He assaulted an officer of the law
他打了朝廷官吏
and should be remanded to General Wang.
按照国法  应该把他交王将军处置
Hui Wen, what do you think?
慧文  你说说看
The Scripture Hall has long been my responsibility.
藏经楼一直是由弟子管
If Chiu Ming trespassed there,
邱明居然能进去  这是弟子失职
I am at fault.
弟子应该负责
But I don't understand how it was
不过  弟子不明白
that Lieutenant Chang happened to be there.
张指挥到藏经楼去干什么
Leave that aside for now.
不要说这些了
And you, Hui Ssu?
慧思  你说说
Punish him!
要重罚
May I ask why?
请问三师傅  什么理由呢
Because that's the only way to satisfy General Wang.
不重罚  王将军和张指挥的气难消
Bind Chiu Ming to the Scripture Hall.
把邱明吊在藏经楼上
General, I fear the Abbot
将军  你这招恶人先告状
is onto your scheme.
智严老住持看穿了
He's a senile old man in his 90s, he won't see through it.
他九十多岁了  糊里糊涂的看不穿
He's not senile in the least.
他一点儿也不糊涂
And Wu Wai is suspicious too.
还有  悟外的话多厉害
It isn't looking good.
这事有点不妙
Only you and Chiu Ming know what happened.
这件事  只有你和邱明知道
He's tied to the Scripture Hall.
他现在绑在藏经楼上
Wait a bit, then go and finish him off.
等会儿你去把他一了百了
Jump!
跳下去
Why are you freeing me?
施主  为什么放我下来
By order of Esquire Wen -
是文安让我放你的
he wants to befriend you.
他想跟你结个善缘
Isn't this in defiance of the Abbot's orders?
这样会不会违背师父的原意
Not at all.
不会
It won't work.
不妥当
Why not?
怎么
Killing Chiu Ming would be of no avail.
把邱明除了  于事无补啊
A murder while we were here
再说  庙里出了人命
would reflect badly on us.
有你我在场  传出去不好听呐
We came for the scroll,
咱们是为了那个卷子来的
let's not complicate matters.
不能节外生枝
You're right.
也对
Forget it.
那就算了
General, go to the Abbot immediately
将军  你要立刻到老禅师那里
and ask him to release Chiu Ming.
替邱明讲情  把他放下来
You'll make a good impression.
这样可以结个善缘
I can't go back on what I said earlier.
我出尔反尔  这怎么行呢
You can!
行
Your Reverence,
难道让我说
yesterday my anger blinded me.
老禅师  我昨天是在气头上
I didn't think Chiu Ming would be treated so harshly.
没想到使邱明受这么重的惩罚
Now I regret it. Can you pardon him?
我有点儿后悔了  你饶了他吧
General, he deserves his punishment.
将军  他是罪有应得
He's been there for hours.
已经吊了几个时辰了
Surely he's suffered enough.
也够他受的了
Can't he be released now?
不如  现在把他放下来吧
It's getting late. Perhaps the General should rest.
时候不早了  将军也该休息了
We'll discuss this another time.
好好  再说吧
See the General out.
你送送将军
Yes.
是
Goodnight.
我不打搅了
General...
将军
Yes?
什么事
Tomorrow the monks will be tested
从明天起  庙里的和尚论经证道
and a new abbot will be chosen.
然后推举新住持
Please be there to advise us.
到时候  想请将军光临指导
Certainly.
我一定来
Gentleman, have you studied
他们三个人的答卷
the three disciples' answers?
二位都看过了吧
Yes.
看过了
All excellent.
都很好
General, what do you think?
将军觉得怎么样
Their answers are all very good.
看下来  他们答的都不错
Approach!
过来
Of all the temple's monks, you three
这几天看下来  庙里几百位弟子
have the best knowledge of Buddhism.
你们三个人论经证道成就最高
Each of you is worthy of the abbot ship.
都能主持本寺的大局
Now His Reverence must make a decision.
现在  请老禅师定夺
The three of you go to the pond behind the temple
你们三个人到庙后边池塘
and each fetch a bucket of clear water.
每人打一桶清水回来
Will do.
是
Is the water in your buckets clear?
你们的桶里是清水吗
Hui Tung, tell me
慧通  你说说
how you got your clear water?
你这清水是怎么打的
Only by working with my brothers
弟子和师弟们同心合力
was I able to obtain clear water.
才打到一桶清水
Explain your answer.
你解给我听
Only when the many streams
就像千溪万水
have run to the sea
同归大海
does it reflect the full moon.
才能照出一轮明月
Hui Wen?
慧文  你呢
I filtered the water through fine gauze...
弟子是用细纱滤出来的
for only by ridding oneself of worldly ideas
这就像修持有恒  澄清俗虑
can one rediscover his true nature.
才能返本归真
Hui Ssu?
慧思
Let nature take its course...
听其自然
clear heart, clear water.
心清水自清
Hui Ssu!
慧思
Come forward!
你过来
Come, come.
来来来
This is a large temple, with many monks.
自从五祖弘忍之后
Therefore, to avoid internal disputes,
为了怕起争端  衣钵误传
an outsider shall become the new abbot.
本寺因为庙大人多
He shall assume the mantle of leadership.
仍然把架裟交给新住持  作为信物
Chiu Ming!
邱明
Chiu Ming! Come forth!
邱明  你过来
Kneel.
跪下
Henceforth, you shall be called Hui Ming.
从现在起  你法名上慧下明
You shall take my place
接替我主持三宝
in upholding temple traditions
你要承先启后
and propagating Buddhist doctrine.
传法度人
Rise!
起来
Now?
现在就来吧
Hui Ming has been chosen as the new abbot.
从现在起  邱明就是本寺的新住持
Respect him as you would the old abbot.
你们要像待师父一样的待他
Turn!
转过去
Bow.
拜
Abbot Hui Ming is now in charge.
慧明住持升坐
These are the temple's accounts.
这是万年册  本庙契约  帐目
Hui Wen will answer any questions you have.
不明白的地方去问慧文
This is Tripitaka's Mahayana Sutra.
这是玄奘法师的《大乘起信论》残卷
It has long been a source of trouble here.
这张纸  多年来惹了不少是非
Deal with it properly.
你要妥为处理
Surely.
是
Tomorrow the old Abbot will retire...
师父涅槃的时候要诵弥陀经
to prepare for Nirvana.
明天一早
We will see him off to South Mountain
智严禅师在南山已于涅槃
by reciting the Amitabha Sutra.
到时候  颂弥陀经
This is absurd! A convict as abbot!
岂有此理  流犯当住持
It's completely inappropriate!
这成什么体统
He'll find it's not easy being abbot.
没那么容易  不给他点儿颜色看看
He still has me to reckon with!
他也不知道我有多大道行
Gentlemen, please excuse me.
二位  我到前边儿去看看
Very well.
请便
I pity him.
- 也真可怜  - 谁呀
Hui Tung. All his efforts were in vain.
慧通白忙了一场
A monk so power hungry
出家人这么热衷权位
isn't fit to be abbot.
就不配当住持
Should I have a talk with the old abbot?
你看我要不要跟智严说说
About what?
说什么呀
To suggest he appoint Hui Tung instead.
请他改派慧通当住持
On what grounds?
什么理由
As district governor I won't allow
就说  我是地方官
a convict to serve as abbot.
在我治内的庙里  由一个流犯当住持
I simply won't allow it.
我不能同意
Don't do it!
千万不要
We have to win Chiu Ming over now.
现在最要紧的是笼络邱明
How? He hates our guts.
他现在恨你我入骨  怎么笼络
I'll see to it.
我去
Over here! Gather around.
过来  大伙儿都过来
Hui Tung has something to say.
大师哥有话跟你们说
Listen...
你们听我说啊
Huh?
怎么
Listen to Hui Tung.
听大师哥讲
Speak of this to no one!
你们可千万别把这事告诉别人
Lead them to the new abbot.
等会儿  你带头去见住持
Tell him you're not getting enough to eat
你们就说吃不饱  菜不够
and you're weak from hunger.
没油水  手脚发软
Raise a ruckus. I'll back you up.
撒开了跟他吵  不用怕
Come on! Let's give him hell!
行  给他来个下马威
Good. I'll leave it to you.
就这么着了  我先走了
Count on us!
你放心
Is there any other business today?
今天还有什么事吗
We captured a smuggler this morning.
早上抓到一个山贼  在前院
Your Reverence.
住持
What is it, Lieutenant?
张指挥  有什么事吗
What happened between us earlier
上一次的事儿  实在是出于误会
was a misunderstanding.
让住持受了点儿委屈
I'm sorry you suffered for it.
我一直耿耿于怀
I've already forgotten it
那件事  贫僧早就忘了
and I hope you'll forget it too.
施主千万不要挂在心上
There's something else you should know.
还有件事儿  我不知道应不应该说
Please speak freely, sir.
施主有话尽管说
The food here is...
贵宝寺的伙食  实在太
What?
什么
The food here in the temple is awful.
贵宝寺的伙食  一向很差
All the monks are complaining.
和尚们都有怨言
I just overheard Hui Tung inciting them
刚才我听到慧通师傅煽风点火
to confront you about it.
叫大伙儿都跟住持来闹事
I've come to let you know
我特地来给您送个信
so you won't be taken by surprise.
你心里要有个底
How can you let us starve?
我们吃不饱怎么行呢
What does it matter?
这有什么关系
What if it goes too far?
我们真要这么办啊
Don't worry! Hui Tung will back us up!
有大师哥兜着了  怕什么
Yes!
是呀
What if he doesn't?
那到时候  要是他不认帐呢
We'll leave the monk hood!
最多还俗  不干了
Easy to say! How would we get by?
你说得倒容易  还俗吃什么
A bowl of gruel isn't hard to come by.
到哪儿去混两顿粥还不容易
If you two want to back out,
你们那么三心两意的
let's just forget it!
咱们这出戏  干脆甭唱了
Your Reverence! We'd like a word with you.
住持  我们有点儿事  想跟您谈一谈
Very well.
好
Is it about the food?
是不是伙食的事
Yes!
是
You still want to go through with it?
你还要跟着吵啊
Master, you know what we eat.
住持  大伙吃什么  你也知道
- I do. - Watery gruel,
- 我知道  - 没菜  没油水
and little else!
连粥都喝不饱
Monks are falling sick every day!
每月都病倒了好几个
They're weak and can't see well at night.
手脚发软  夜里看不见
Sick? We're starving!
什么病啊  饿的
Ravaged by hunger!
饿得我气都发虚
What's going on here?
干什么  干什么
What's all the shouting about?
你们吵什么  有什么好吵的
Quiet?
不要吵了
We'll find a way to improve the food,
伙食的事  咱们想办法改
but there'll be other changes as well.
可是别的也要改
From now on, monks will not spend
从现在起  这庙里的和尚
the entire day in contemplation.
不能整天念经打坐
They'll do farm work as well.
要种庄稼  种菜
Plant crops?
种庄稼
Monks farming? Is he serious?
这和尚种庄稼  我还没听说过
Quiet!
别吵
Your Reverence,
住持
I don't think it will work.
叫他们种地  这恐怕行不通吧
Yes, it will.
行得通
We don't know how to farm!
我们不会种庄稼
Then learn.
不会就学
From whom?
跟谁学
I'll teach you.
跟我学
Disperse now.
你们去吧
We need more food!
那伙食还改不改
How can we farm on empty stomachs?
我们吃不饱怎么行呢
- He's left. - Let's go.
- 人都走了  - 走了
Solving the food problem won't be easy.
住持  这改伙食可不简单呐
You've seen the temple accounts.
刚才我跟您报过帐了
What we take in barely covers expenses.
咱们庙里的收入有限  花费有定数
We don't have the money for more food.
这一改伙食  钱就不够用了
Then go collect alms.
那就去化缘
I'm in charge of alms collection.
化缘的事  本来都是我去办
Money's scarce this year!
可是年头不好  化不动啊
Then borrow!
那就去借
Your Reverence!
住持
We've nothing to put up for collateral
那就更难了  再说借要有抵押
unless we go to Esquire Wen.
除非请文居士想办法
Then go to him now.
好  现在就去
Your Reverence, the food situation...
住持  这改伙食的事
It will be rectified tomorrow.
明天一定改
These are the ones.
就是这几个
They've been eating meat and drinking wine.
他们偷着喝酒  吃肉
He's their supplier.
每趟都是那个人运进来的
We caught them this morning.
今天早上给抓着了
Where did they get the money?
他们哪儿来的钱
From Hui Wen.
二师哥给的
Brother, what are you saying?
师弟  这是什么话
They confessed to it.
他们自己招的
I sent them to buy provisions.
我叫他们采办伙食
I didn't tell them to break their vows!
我没有叫他们去犯戒
How were such matters handled in the past?
慧通  以前这种事怎么办
For monks, three months of solitary confinement.
庙里的人罚面壁三个月
For laypeople, a severe caning.
外边儿的人  吊起来打十二板子
I'll take care of it.
这事您交给我好了
Fine. But we'll initiate a new procedure.
好  咱们改个办法
Monks will go to the rear courtyard
庙里的人  到后院把井边那块地铲平
and clear land to plant vegetables.
种上大白菜
Turn the smuggler over to Lieutenant Chang
那个外边儿的人  交给张诚
to await trial.
等地方官来发落
- Your Reverence... - Do as I say.
- 住持  - 就这么办了
Go now!
你现在就去
- Take care of it immediately! - Yes, sir.
- 你们要立刻办好  - 是
How dare you defame me?
你怎么胡说八道的
Your Reverence.
住持
Esquire Wen.
施主
I was on my way to see you.
贫僧正要找你
And I was just on my way to congratulate you
住持  我刚才就想过去给您道贺
but I saw you were very busy.
看见您忙
No congratulations, please.
出家人不讲究这些
Esquire...
施主
we want to improve the food here.
庙里要改善一下伙食
Can you help us?
想请施主帮帮忙
I'd help if I could,
应该的  应该的
but as Hui Wen knows,
不过最近景况实在是紧
I'm having difficulties myself.
二师傅知道的
Well...
那么
could you help us borrow?
能不能请施主  到外边儿斋借斋借
Lenders want collateral for loans.
放款的人多数要抵押
We could mortgage the temple property.
那么就把庙里的地契押给他们
The lenders wouldn't accept it.
生意人怎么敢收庙契呢
Why not?
怎么
If you defaulted, they couldn't sell the temple.
万一不还钱  他们也不能把庙给卖了
Is there any other way?
还有别的办法吗
With the Tripitaka scroll as security,
那部玄奘法师手抄的卷子
you could borrow a large sum.
倒能押不少钱
How much?
能押多少
Tens of thousands of taels of silver.
几万两银子  大概能押吧
Fine. First give Hui Wen a draft for 10,000 taels.
好  你先写一万两银票给慧文
As for the scroll,
那部卷子
let me think about it.
我  我想想看
Here are two drafts, each worth 10,000 taels.
这是两万两银票  一张是你的
One for the temple, one for you.
一张是公款
And here's the key to Scripture Hall.
这是藏经楼的钥匙
If he changes his mind, resort to your original plan.
万一他变卦  你再下手
Madame!
如夫人
If they steal it,
现在要能到手
it won't cost me anything.
连一万两银子都省了
Let's go.
走
How can I explain a murder in the temple?
这将来庙里出了人命怎么办呢
Leave it to me!
有我呢
But he's the abbot!
无论如何  他是住持
You go first.
你先去
Understand?
这你该明白了吧
On my own I'm no match for him.
指挥  我怕一个人弄不过他
Don't worry. I've got your back.
别怕  有我给你打接应
Go on! Go!
去吧  去去去去
Your Reverence!
住持
Madame.
施主
Hui Tung and Chang Cheng are plotting to kill you!
慧通  张诚要害你  留神点儿
Put some salve on it and you'll be fine.
你不用怕  马上找点儿刀创药擦上
Then go watch over the Scripture Hall tonight.
然后睡在藏经楼门口
If there's any trouble there,
今天晚上  藏经楼要是出了什么事
I'll hold you responsible.
明天唯你是问
Now go!
去吧
Have you seen Chang Cheng?
有没有看见张诚
Go out the back. Meet me at the riverside.
走后门  河边儿见
See you there!
河边儿见
Esquire Wen,
- 将军  - 文兄啊
I...
我
Well, this has been an eventful visit.
我们这一趟总算是功德圆满了
Indeed it has.
是呀  是呀
Are you leaving today too, General?
将军也是今天下山吗
Yes. I've official duties to attend to.
马上就走
Then I won't delay you further.
那我就不另外辞行了
You're too polite!
不要客气  不要客气
- Goodbye.
- 再见  - 再见  再见
- After you. - Please.
- 请  - 请
Chang Cheng!
张诚
"White Fox has scroll. In pursuit.
狐盗卷逃  直追
Await you at riverside."
河边候驾
Damn it! Where by the riverside?
河边
Hurry!
走
Run!
快跑
What about Gold Lock?
- 金锁呢  - 走
Chang Cheng.
张诚
Isn't this Gold Lock?
这不是金锁吗
After them!
搜
Come on!
走
I say, sir, can you ferry us across?
老大爷  您渡我们过江好吧
I'll pay you 10 taels of silver.
我给您十两银子
20, then!
好  二十两
All right?
好吧
Let's go!
走吧
Hurry!
快点儿开船
Wait!
等一等
What?
- 干嘛  - 还没给他钱呢
On second thought...
不对
What if he betrays us?
这老头一会儿告诉他们就糟了
Better yet...
不如
That won't do!
这不大好吧
Old fellow, I forgot to pay you.
老大爷  还没给您钱呢
Old fellow, over here, over here!
老大爷  您过来  过来呀
Please, sir... stop!
二位施主  请留步
Esquire Wen.
施主
Brother Hui Wen.
慧文师傅
I've told the Abbot all about our plot.
我跟你的事  我都对住持说了
You stole and murdered on temple grounds.
现在你在庙里偷了东西  又杀了人
How will you account for that?
这怎么了结呢
Chang Cheng attacked me!
是张诚先动的手啊
But you've no proof of it!
那是死无对证啊
Chang Cheng was a known killer.
张诚是有名的酷吏
The brute got what he deserved.
他一向作恶多端  死有余辜啊
That may indeed be so,
这在情理上也许说得过去
but the law won't see it that way!
在国法上可讲不通啊
Then... what can I do?
那  那到这个地步  我
Return with me and beg for the Abbot's mercy.
文施主  你还是跟我回去  求求住持
Perhaps he'll be lenient.
也许能够从轻发落
So... all my efforts were in vain?
那  那这趟我不是白来了
I'm afraid so.
我看是白来了
Go to hell!
哎呀
Esquire Wen!
文施主
Esquire! Not that way...!
文施主  那儿不能去啊
This tattered parchment
这张烂纸
has caused trouble for far too long.
多少年来是本寺祸乱之源
Now I'm returning it to Tripitaka.
现在  我把它还给玄奘法师
General Wang.
王将军
The Mahayana Sutra's true value is in its meaning.
《大乘起信论》可贵之处  在它的文意
It should be available to all.
它应该广为传播
I've made scores of copies.
师父早已经印好了几十份
One of them for you, General.
现在  送给将军一份
Call her over to take the tonsure.
叫她过来  给她剃度
Come.
你过来
Kneel!
跪下
Chant the sutra.
诵经